Guide to the Howell Wright Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence, 1886-1954; Series I
  - Newman, W. F. H., 1940 (Box 18, Folder 348)
  - Newton, Francis J., 1935-1948 (Box 18, Folder 349)
  - Nicholls, James E., 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 350)
  - Niven, Cecily, 1930, 1935-1938 (Box 18, Folder 351)
  - Niven, D., 1936, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 352)
  - Nourse, Henry, 1936-1938 (Box 18, Folder 353)
  - O'Dell, Edward St. John, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 354)
  - Olivier, J. H., 1901 (Box 18, Folder 355)
  - Oppenheimer, Ernest, 1936-1949 (Box 18, Folder 356)
  - Packer, Launcelot, 1935-1937 (Box 18, Folder 357)
  - Paddon, Cecil, 1946-1953 (Box 18, Folder 358)
  - Palmer, J. A., 1937-1938, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 359)
  - Phillips, Lady Florence, 1927, 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 360)
  - Pickstone, H. E. U., 1937-1938 (Box 18, Folder 361)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1924-1925 (Box 18, Folder 362)
  - Pioneers, Mashonaland (Rhodesia), 1890 (Box 18, Folder 363)
  - Pirow, Oswald, 1952-1953 (Box 19, Folder 364)
  - Playfair, W. R., 1949, 1953 (Box 19, Folder 365)
  - Pomerene, Atlee, 1922 (Box 19, Folder 366)
  - Preller, G. S., 1935 (Box 19, Folder 367)
  - Pringle Family, 1938-1951 (Box 19, Folder 368)
  - Radziwell, Princess, 1946-1950 (Box 19, Folder 369)
  - Rand Pioneer Album See: box 24, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 370 - 371)
  - Rand, Richard Frank, 1937-1938 (Box 19, Folder 372)
  - Raphall, Lois A. C., 1937-1943 (Box 19, Folder 373)
  - Rawson, Alice Evelyn, 1889 (Box 19, Folder 374)
  - Reeve, C. E., 1936-1942 (Box 19, Folder 375)
  - Reitz, Deneys, 1935-1936 (Box 19, Folder 376)
  - Reitz, Johannes H. B., 1868, 1925, 1939 (Box 19, Folder 377)
  - Rhodes, Cecil John
    - Correspondence, 1871-1908 (Box 19, Folder 378 - 379)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 19, Folder 380)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 20, Folder 381)
    - Wills, Confession of Faith, 1877, 1882-1896 (Box 20, Folder 382)
    - Rhodes Birthplace Memorial, undated (Box 20, Folder 383)
    - Rhodes Memorial Ceremony, 1941-1945 (Box 20, Folder 384)
  - Rhodes, Francis William, 1938-1939 (Box 20, Folder 385)
  - Rhodesia Herald, 1936-1940 (Box 20, Folder 386)
  - Robins, Herbert G., 1939 (Box 20, Folder 387)
  - Robins, T. Ellis, 1940-1946 (Box 20, Folder 388)
  - Robinson, Joseph B., 1938-1939 (Box 20, Folder 389)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (U. S. President), 1937 (Box 20, Folder 390)
  - Rose-Innes, Sir James, 1937-1938 (Box 20, Folder 391)
  - Ross, John, 1938 (Box 20, Folder 392)
  - Ross, Thomas A., 1937-1943 (Box 20, Folder 393)
  - Rouillard, Nancy Thompson, 1937-1938 (Box 20, Folder 394)
  - Roux, Fanny, 1937-1938 (Box 20, Folder 395)
  - Rudd, Percy, 1936-1940, 1948 (Box 20, Folder 396)
  - Rudland, Thomas W., 1937-1951 (Box 20, Folder 397)
  - Russell, Archer, 1937, 1941-1943 (Box 21, Folder 398)
  - Rutland, Violet, Duchess of Rutland, 1937 (Box 21, Folder 399)
  - Tylett, S. H., 1938 (Box 21, Folder 400)
  - Sampson, Victor, 1937-1938 (Box 21, Folder 401)
  - Sauer, J. W., undated (Box 21, Folder 402)
  - Schoof, Guston H., 1939 (Box 21, Folder 403)
  - Schreiner, William F. R., 1939 (Box 21, Folder 404)
  - Scully, W. C., 1938-1945 (Box 21, Folder 405)
  - Selous, F. C., 1902, 1906 (Box 21, Folder 406)
  - Selous, F. C., 1936-1937 (Box 21, Folder 407)
  - Seymour, Charles, 1944, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 408)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1900 (Box 21, Folder 409)
  - Shed, William Burns, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 410)
  - Sheffield, Jessie Fraser, 1938-1939 (Box 21, Folder 411)
  - Shepstone, Francis Alan, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 412)
  - Shepstone, Sidney N. S., 1951 (Box 21, Folder 413)
  - Shiras, Winfield, 1936 (Box 21, Folder 414)
  - Sibbett, Cecil J., 1937-1953 (Box 21, Folder 415 - 416)
  - Smart, Lady Sybil A., 1928-1929, 1936-1945 (Box 21, Folder 417)
  - Smith, R. Carruthers, 1937, 1948-1953 (Box 21, Folder 418)
  - Smuts, Jan Christian, 1935-1947 (Box 21, Folder 419)
  - Southern Rhodesia government, 1937-1954 (Box 21, Folder 420 - 421)
  - Stent, Vere Palgrave, 1927-1931, 1936-1942 (Box 22, Folder 422)
  - Steytler, Jourens J., 1939 (Box 22, Folder 423)
  - Struben, Georgia, 1938 (Box 22, Folder 424)
  - Sunderland, J. C., 1939
  - Symons, L. H., 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 425)
  - Tabler, Edward C., 1944-1945 (Box 22, Folder 426)
  - Taylor, James E., 1936 (Box 22, Folder 427)
  - Taylor, William P., 1936-1941 (Box 22, Folder 428)
  - Thomas W. E., 1929, 1936-1938 (Box 22, Folder 429)
  - Thomas, A. R., 1938 (Box 22, Folder 430)
  - Thompson, Francis R. "Matabele", 1926 (Box 22, Folder 431)
  - Townsend, Reynold Whitcombe, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 432)
  - Transvaal Chamber of Mines, undated (Box 22, Folder 433)
  - Tredgold, Sir Robert C., 1953-1954 (Box 22, Folder 434)
  - Trek: Great Trek, Founding of Orange River Colony, 1937 (Box 22, Folder 435)
  - Tullock, Alexander "Sandy", 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 436)
  - Tyndale-Biscoe, E. C., 1936-1938 (Box 22, Folder 437)
  - Union of South Africa, 1944-1952 (Box 22, Folder 438)
  - Vander Byl, G. U., 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 439)
  - Venables, J. W. E., 1937-1953 (Box 22, Folder 440)
  - Vialls, C. Clements, 1937 (Box 22, Folder 441)
  - Walker, Eric A., 1935-1938 (Box 22, Folder 442)
  - Walton, Edgar Harris, 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 443)
  - Warren, Albert H., 1937-1938 (Box 22, Folder 444)
  - Warth, T. H., 1951 (Box 22, Folder 445)
  - Weale, M. E., 1937-1939, 1946 (Box 22, Folder 446)
  - Webber, H. O'K., 1909, 1937-1947 (Box 22, Folder 447)
  - Wells, Charles Edward, 1938 (Box 22, Folder 448)
  - White, Charles James, 1938-1940 (Box 22, Folder 449)
  - Williams, Apheus F., 1936-1939 (Box 23, Folder 450)
  - Williams, Arthur Vaughn, 1942, 1944 (Box 23, Folder 451)
  - Williams, Basil, 1936-1939 (Box 23, Folder 452)
  - Williams, Sir Robert, 1936-1938 (Box 23, Folder 453)
  - Willkie, Wendell L., 1944 (Box 23, Folder 454)
  - Wilson, B. Matabele, 1936, 1946-1949 (Box 23, Folder 455)
  - Wilson Family (George H. & Arthur N.), 1946, 1950-1952 (Box 23, Folder 456)
  - Wilson Patrol (Shangani), 1935-1936 (Box 23, Folder 457)
  - Windram, R. F., 1938-1940 (Box 23, Folder 458)
  - Wolf. H. A., 1886, 1896 (Box 23, Folder 459)
  - Worthington, Frank, 1936-1951 (Box 23, Folder 460)
  - Wright, Howell
    - General, 1907-1942 (Box 23, Folder 461)
    - Africa, South: trip, 1945-1946 (Box 23, Folder 462 - 464)
    - Wright Collection, 1925-1954 (Box 23, Folder 465)
    - Writings, undated (Box 23, Folder 466)
  - Wylie, Sir Francis, 1944-1945 (Box 23, Folder 467)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 23, Folder 468)
  - Rand Pioneer Album (Box 24)
- Photographs, 1890-1902; Series II
  This series is arranged in two sections:Rhodes, Cecil John andSouth Africa.
  - Rhodes, Cecil John
    - 1-100 (Box 25, Folder 469 - 474)
    - 101-200 (Box 26, Folder 475 - 479)
    - 201-290 (Box 27, Folder 480 - 484)
  - South Africa
    - Albums, 1895-1896 (Box 28)
    - Fry, W. Ellington (Box 29)
    - Rhodes, Ernest Frederick (Box 30)
    - Wright, Howell: Collection, 1952, 1899-1902 (Box 31, Folder 485 - 487)
    - 1890 Expedition to Mashonaland, Pioneer Corps (Box 32, Folder 488 - 495)
- Printed Material, 1900-1950; Series III
  This series is arranged by topic, and chronologically within each topic.
  - South Africa (Box 33, Folder 496 - 500)
  - General (Box 33, Folder 501)
- Personal Papers, 1910-1953; Series IV
  This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Books
    - Family (Box 34, Folder 502)
    - Sauer, Hans, 1938 (Box 34, Folder 503)
  - Clippings
    - General, 1910-1953, undated (Box 34, Folder 504)
    - Rhodes, Cecil John (Box 34, Folder 505)
  - Printed Material, 1934-1953, undated (Box 34, Folder 506)
  - Miscellanea (Box 34, Folder 507)
  - Miscellanea, 1931 (Box 35, Folder 508)
- Oversize
  - British South Africa Company, 1890 (Box 36)
  - Jameson, Leander Starr, 1895 (Box 36)
  - Maund, E. A., 1885-1892 (Box 36)
  - Pretoria, Union of South Africa, 1891-1900 (Box 36)
  - Wilson, B. Matabele, 1885 (Box 36)
  - Miscellanea: printed material, documents, and writings (photostats), undated (Box 37)
- Additional Material, circa 1860s-1925; Accession 1996-M-093
  This addition to the Howell Wright Collection consists of photographs and sketches of Cecil John Rhodes and his family, friends, and colleagues. The inventory is based on one by Howell Wright and consists of two lists, A and B. The number to the immediate left of each photograph description is also on the back of that item.
  - List A
    - Copy of original listing (Box 1)
    - #1,2--[On Wright's list with notation "Framed" but not received in this accession] (Box 1)
    - #3--Cecil J. Rhodes [reproduction of a miniature] (Box 1)
    - #3a--Bishop's Stortford, England [birthplace of Rhodes] (Box 1)
    - #4--Bust of Rhodes [done by Henry A. Pegram] (Box 1)
    - #5--Rhodes [in cricket costume, holding bat, probably ten years old] (Box 1)
    - #6--Rhodes [from a painting by Mortimer Menpes] (Box 1)
    - #7--Snapshot of Rhodes (Box 1)
    - #8--Rhodes, Thomas Smartt, and others in the Matopos [Lobengula's son standing in background] (Box 1)
    - #9--Rhodes playing chess on board ship (Box 1)
    - #10--Rhodes and Kitchener leaving Oxford wearing cap and gown (Box 1)
    - #11--Rhodes, Jack Grimmer, and body servant, Tony (Box 1)
    - #12--Rhodes and others as Oxford students outside of Oriel College [Rhodes on extreme left], 1876 (Box 1)
    - #13--Rhodes as a boy, on horseback outside his father's church at Bishop's Stortford (Box 1)
    - #14--Rhodes at Groote Schuur [his home in South Africa] (Box 1)
    - #15--Rhodes and Jameson (both in flannel trousers) with others at Aswan Dam, Egypt [Rhodes has white umbrella] (Box 1)
    - #16--Rhodes as Prime Minister and others sitting in House of Assembly, Cape Town (Box 1)
    - #17--Rhodes and groups of DeBeers directors and officials at annual meeting, 1894 (Box 1)
    - #18--Rhodes (in white flannel trousers) and a Kimberley, South Africa, group photograph (Box 1)
    - #19--same as above (Box 1)
    - #20--DeBeers group including Rhodes, life director; W. H. Craven, secretary; Gardner F. Williams, general manager; G. W. Compton, director; C. E. Nind, director; H. Rubinow, and Lt. Col. D. Harris (Box 1)
    - #21-25--Rhodes at different ages (Box 1)
    - #26--Rhodes cutting the first sod of the Port Elizabeth Bowling Green (Box 1)
    - #27--Country house party (Box 1)
    - #28--Rhodes and Sir Charles Metcalfe ["Landing at Cape Town from the R. M. S. Briton,"1902; about two months before his death] (Box 2)
    - #29--Rhodes [from a painting by Sir W. Nicholson] (Box 2)
    - #30--"In the Drakenstein C. J. Rhodes" (Box 2)
    - #31--Rhodes [from a painting by Mortimer Menpes; enlargement of photograph #6] (Box 2)
    - #32--Rhodes at his choice of burial site in the Matopos (Box 2)
    - #33--Sketch by Duchess of Rutland (Box 2)
    - #34--Rhodes [from a painting by Rowarth, Professor of Fine Arts] (Box 2)
    - #35-- Vanity Fair cartoons (Box 2)
      - "The Goldon Idol", 1895 December 25 (Box 2)
      - "A Good Joke", 1896 December 25 (Box 2)
      - "The Lord Chancellors Stall", 1901 December 25 (Box 2)
      - "The Cape", 1891 March 28 (Box 2)
      - "Empire Makers & Breakers", 1897 (Box 2)
    - #36--Rhodes's cottage, Cape Town (Box 1)
  - List B
    - #1--[On Wright's list with notation "Not sending"; however, item is the same as #9 on List A] (Box 1)
    - #2--Autographed photograph from J. Grimmer to Rhodes (Box 1)
    - #3--Dr. Jameson and friends, Richard Solomon, Searle, Jameson, and William Solomon, Chief Justice of the Union of South Africa (Box 1)
    - #4--Sir Leander Starr Jameson [portrait painted by his brother, Middleton; original in National Portrait Gallery, London] (Box 1)
    - #5--Doctor Jameson (Box 1)
    - #6--Jameson with members of the South African National Convention which drafted the Constitution for the Union of South Africa, Durban (Box 2)
    - #7--Jameson and members of the "Raid" on board S. S. Victoria, 1896 (Box 1)
    - #8--Sir Starr Jameson, Bart., C. B. administrator of Mashonaland and Matabeleland (Box 1)
    - #9--Alfred Breit [from painting by Alfred Hayward], 1925 (Box 1)
    - #10--Jameson [from painting by Edward Rowarth, Cape Town], 1911 (Box 2)
    - #11--High School, Bishop's Stortford [includes E. F. Rhodes and C. J. Rhodes], 1869 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-086
  - Pamphlets about Cecil John Rhodes by Howell Wright
    - "Cecil John Rhodes through American Eyes", 1946 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Living Spirit of Cecil John Rhodes: Crusader-Statesman-World Citizen", 1945 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlets about Cecil John Rhodes by other authors, 1941-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rhodes, Cecil John
    - Clippings, 1939, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia [including C. J. Rhodes bookplate and postcards], 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Anatomy of Terror", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Background Briefing: The Extent of British Influence on the Rhodesian Situation", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Background Briefing: Terrorists, Missionaries and the West", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Bloody Love," by V. W. Van Rijnberk, [ca. 1971] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "For Kith and Kin?", [ca. 1976] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - For the record
    - No. 16: "Rhodesia Settlement Proposals: Courage and Faith Needed", 1972 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 17: "The Pearce Commission Report: Broadcast Statement by the Prime Minister, the Hon. I. D. Smith and a Statement by the Rhodesian Government, 23rd May, 1972", 1972 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 22: "Prime Minister's Statement on the Settlement Issue, 29th June, 1973", 1973 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 23: "Prime Minister's Statement on the Constitutional Dispute, Settlement Proposals and African Opinion. 19th June, 1974", 1974 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 24: "Judgment [A judgment concerning the necessity or expediency of continuing the detention of the Reverend Ndabaningi Sithole who was the subject of a detention order issued on the 3rd day of March, 1975.]", 1975 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 25: "Prime Minister's Speech at the Opening of Trade FairRhodesia, 1975" (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 26: "Prime Minister's Interview with Richard Kershaw, B.B.C. 'Panorama'", 1975 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 33: "Press Interview with the Prime Minister of Rhodesia", 1976 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 34: "Press Conference held by Minister of Defence and Foreign Affairs, Mr. Pieter Van Der Byl", 1976 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 39: "Prime Minister's Address to the Nation", 1977 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 39, Supplement: "British Proposals for a Transitional Government in Rhodesia", 1977 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - No. 40: "Removal of Racial Discrimination: Prime Minister's Statement in Parliament", 1977 February (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Harvest of Fear: A Diary of Terrorist Atrocities in Rhodesia", 1976 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Other Side of the Coin", 1976 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Recent Developments in Rhodesia's Tribal Trust Lands" [2 copies], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Red for Danger", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rhodesia and the Anglo-American Proposals", 1977 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Rhodesian Republican Constitution: Its Acceptability by the Rhodesian People", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rhodesia's Case", 1970 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Rhodesia's Tribal Areas", 1971 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Safeguards for a Settlement", 1977 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Settlement Proposals--An Explanation, [ca. 1969] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Where did Pearce go wrong? A Brief Appreciation of the Pearce Report", 1972 June (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-009
  The accession includes Rhodesian Information Service leaflets and pamphlets.
  Existence and Location of Originals
  See Accession 2005-M-086
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-028
  - "Cecil Rhodes, South African Empire Builder" by Rafael Sabatini [photocopy of biography article no. 5 in series, Heroes of Empire, published in the Over-seas Daily Mail ], 1936 January 4-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of men prominent in South African affairs [Cecil Rhodes not included] Listed alphabetically: Abe Bailey; Alfred Beit; P. W. Botha; Rowan Cashel; F. Drummond Chaplain; P. B. Clements; Johann W. Colenbrander; A. R. Colquhoun; Edmund Davis; Lawson L. B. Dykes; John Fraser; Edward C. F. Garraway; Earl Grey; Piet Grobler; James Hertzog; A. H. J. Hore; Jameson Raid Group and newspaper illustration, "The Trial of Dr. Jameson and His Officers," The Daily Graphic, 1896 Jul 29; Johannesburg Reform Committee; Arthur Lawley; William Milton, Ernest Oppenheimer, Hans Sauer; Thomas N. Smartt; F. R. Matabele Thompson; A. J. Tomlinson; Julius Wernher; and Robert Williams], 1891, 1896, 1911, 1914, 1916, 1920, 1938, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2009-M-030
  - American newspaper comments on Jameson's Raid, 1896-1900, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Cecil Rhodes Calls America" and related materials, 1902, 1944-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Library of Congress, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jameson's Raid, staff officers, British War Office, 1896-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Notes on Jameson's Raid and the Johannesburg Revolution, Circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reform Committee members, Jameson's Raid, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research materials
    - Research and bibliographic notes, Circa 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Essays on General Smuts, Circa 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rhodes, Cecil, Circa 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jameson's Raid and the Reform Committee, Circa 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Transvaal War and the Johannesburg Reform Committee, Circa 1890-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - South African and Rhodesian pioneers, Circa 1890-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)